<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A generall free pardon or Charter of heuyn blys very necessary for all true christe[n] people, wherin standeth clene remission of all our synnes, to all penytent [and] faythfull hertes. Not gyuen by any popysh collusyon, but by Iesu Christ, son of the lyuyng God. Compyled in our old Englyssh tong, in the yere of our lorde God. M. iiii. C. nether addyng to nor dymynysshyng fro, saue only some old wordes, turned into our new maner and accostomed spekyng. God save the Kyng.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1542</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19187</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119987</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855191</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855191</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20667</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08910)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20667)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 716:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A generall free pardon or Charter of heuyn blys very necessary for all true christe[n] people, wherin standeth clene remission of all our synnes, to all penytent [and] faythfull hertes. Not gyuen by any popysh collusyon, but by Iesu Christ, son of the lyuyng God. Compyled in our old Englyssh tong, in the yere of our lorde God. M. iiii. C. nether addyng to nor dymynysshyng fro, saue only some old wordes, turned into our new maner and accostomed spekyng. God save the Kyng.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In saynt Sepulchres paryssh, in the old Baylly by Rychard Lant, for Iohn Gough, dwellyng at Smartes kay besyde byllynges gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1542?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Forgiveness of sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20667:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:20667:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->
            <p>¶A generall free Pardon or Charter of heuyn blys / very neceſſary for all true chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people / wher in ſtandeth clene remiſſion of all our ſynnes / to all penytent &amp; fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hertes. Not gyuen by any popyſh colluſyon / but by Ieſu Chriſt / ſon of the lyuyng God, Compyled in our old Englyſſh tong / in the yere of our lorde God. M.iiii, C. nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther addyng to nor dymynyſſhyng fro / ſaue only ſome old wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / turned into our new maner and accoſtomed ſpekyng. *</p>
            <p>
               <hi>GOD SAVE THE KYNG.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:20667:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Arma Christi</figDesc>
                  <p>I.N.R.I.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pardon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20667:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->
            <head>Here begynneth the pardon or chartre of heuyns blys,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very wyſe man that cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> or deſyreth this heauenl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> aſketh great pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / kepe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſely and hath oft mynd vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the charter of his chale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / &amp; the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lore ech man lerne to lyue vertuouſly / and kepe &amp; haue mynd vpon the chartre of heuens blys / &amp; ſtudy buſely &amp; ſtedfaſtly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyt of this bul for the perdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof ſhal dure w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>oute end therfore vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thou well that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tre of this heritage / &amp; the bul of this euer laſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / is our lord Ieſu chriſt writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with al the myght &amp; vertu of god / The parcheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly chartre / is ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſheep / ne of calfe / but it is the body &amp; the ſkyn of our lord Ieſu chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lamb / that neuer was ſpotted with wem or ſpot of ſyn. &amp; there was neyther ſkyn of ſheep neyther of calfe / ſo ſore &amp; ſo hard ſtrayned on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teyntur / eyther harow of any parche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t maker / as was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed body &amp; ſkyn of our lord Ieſu Chriſt / for our lyfe ſtrey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:20667:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->
&amp; drawen vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the yebet of the croſſe. And ther neuer man herde fro the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the worlde / tyll nowe / neyther ſhal vntyll domes day / that euer wrytes wrote vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhepes ſkyn / eyther on calues with ſo hard &amp; hydous pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nys: ſo bytter ſo ſore or ſo depe / as writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the curſed Iues vpon the bleſſed body &amp; ſwete ſkyn of our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt / with hard nayles &amp; ſharp ſpere / &amp; ſore pryckynge thornes in ſtede of theyr pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nys: for they wrote them ſo ſore &amp; ſo depe / that they perced his han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des and fete with hard nayles / &amp; opened his hart with a ſharpe ſpere / and preſſed vpon his hed a crowne of ſharpe thornes that lyghtly perced his brayne pan. The woundes vpon that bleſſed body &amp; ſwete ſkyn of our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt / were in ſtede of letters / &amp; as clerkes ſayen &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſaynt Ancelme, that there were ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des vpon the bleſſed body of Chriſt by nombre / fyue. M.CCCC.lxxv. this is the nombre of the letters / with which our chartre was wrytten / by the whiche
<pb facs="tcp:20667:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->
chartre we may clayme our herytage (yf we lyue ryghteouſly and kepe this char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre ſtedfaſtly in mynde). The ſentence and vnderſtandyng wrytten within and without this bleſſed chartre / and body of our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt / is our beleue.</p>
            <p>For he is the cofer / in whom is cloſen &amp; locken all the treaſure / wyt &amp; wyſdom of god. Alſo vpon this bleſſed chartre was wrytten / waylyng &amp; mournynge / ſonge &amp; ſorow / for ſorow of our ſynnes: for the which ſinnes to be heled &amp; waſſhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away / Chriſt god and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt ſuffre ſo hard &amp; paynfull woundes: Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſtes body that is our heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly chartre / was wrytten ſygnifieng to al tho that perfytly forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſynnes: for they han full medecyn &amp; helth through vertu of the bytter woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; precious blood of Ieſu. And vpon the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of Ieſu / maye be red ſorow to al them that for fals luſt &amp; lykyng that dureth but a whyle / bynde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf ſo ſore to ſynne &amp; ſeruage of the fende / &amp; leſen, the helpe of theyr heuenly chartre &amp; ſo theyr
<pb facs="tcp:20667:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->
herytage &amp; we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den or go blyndly to ſorow that dureth for euer. The lacys of this heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly chartre / ben beheſtys of god / and that god may not lye / for he is ſouerayne truth. The fyrſt lace is his beheſtys / that what day or ower a ſynful man or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leueth their ſyn / holy &amp; hertly with bitter ſorow &amp; tourne them to him / he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue them to his mercy. But yche man beware that he tary not to longe / leſt for his owne vnkyndnes / grace be taken fro him. The ſecond lace is the ful truſt that we han or haue / that god may not lye / ne ther be fals of his beheſtes: &amp; here in han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth ſyckerly the truſt of our herytage: &amp; by theſe two lacys / ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth the ſele of our charter / ſeled with the bloud of the lambe Chriſt: that is Chriſtes fleſſhe / taken of the cleneſt dropes of bloud / in the ſweteſt virgyn Mary / more craftely and merue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>louſly / than euer any may be by craft of kynde / gather the wax of floures of the felde. The prynt of this ſele / is the ſhap of our lorde Ieſu chriſt / hangyng on the
<pb facs="tcp:20667:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->
croſſe for our ſynnes / as we may ſe by the Image of the Crucyfyx: for he hath his hed bowed downe / redy to kys all thoſe that verely turne to him. Alſo he hath his armys ſpred abrode / redy to be clyp them and he is nayled to the cros faſt / both fete and handes: for he wyll dwell with them and neuer wende away from them: but if they forſake him fyrſt / through ſyn. And he hath al his body ſpred abrode / to gyue him ſelfe holly to vs cleuyng to him / and verely he hath his ſyde openyd / &amp; his hert clouen for our ſake: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> without lettyng we muſt crepe into his herte &amp; reſt there thorow ſtedfaſt beleue &amp; herty loue This charter may no fyer bren / ne water dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch or drowne / neither thefe robbe / neyther any creature deſtroy. For this ſcrypture the father of heuen hath halowed / eyther made ſtedfaſt / and ſent it into the worlde the which ſcrypture may not be vndo / as the goſpel wytneſſeth. This ſcripture is our lord Ieſu chriſtes Charter and Bul of our herytage of heuen. Locke not this
<pb facs="tcp:20667:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->
chartre in thy cofer / but ſet it ether wryts it in thy hert / &amp; all the creatures in heuen neither in erth / neither in hell / maye not rob it / neither bren it from the / but if thou wylt thy ſelfe / aſſentyng to ſyn.</p>
            <p>And if thou kepeſt well this Charter in the cofer of thy hert / with good lyuyng and deuout loue / laſtingly to the end / as truſtly &amp; trewly / as he is true god. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row vertu of this Charter / thou ſhalt ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue thy herytage of blys / that laſteth with outen ende. Now therfore haſt we to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauns / as ſaynt Auſten byddeth / and the laſt day be euer afore our eyen. Refrayne we our bodyes from byces &amp; euyll couey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynges / &amp; euer let our hertes thynke he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly thynges / that whan we come thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / we vſe fully heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly goodes: for why we beleue / that whan our ſoule ſhalbe vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knytted from the bonde of fleſſhe. If we han or haue lyued wel &amp; rightfully before god / anon the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of angels ſhal com into our metynges / &amp; they ſhall bryng vs with worſhyp to the very domyſman.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20667:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->If that we han lyued as I ſayd / than peace ſhalbe to vs &amp; ſykernes in compas Than we ſhall not drede the fyry dartes of the deuyll / neither any other maner e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy that cometh to hurt our ſoules.</p>
            <p>The fleſſhe ſhall no more be aduerſary to the ſpirite / neither we ſhall drede any perels. Than the holy ghoſt ſhal gyue to vs a dwellyng in heuenly thinges / &amp; we glad in ioyfull / &amp; ſhall abyde the daye of dome to com / in which the ſoules of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall receyue meed for their deedes. And than ſhal ſynners and vnpytefull men pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſſhe. But in that day vayne men &amp; ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenours / gredy men &amp; proud men / auou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tres &amp; wrathfull / coueteus / curſers and forſworne men ſhall wepe moſt bytterly / and they ſhal not get forgyuenes of their euels / which left not their ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes with byt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſorow in their lyfe. In moſt waylyng they ſhall be holden / which ſeruyden to vnlefull luſtes of the fleſſh / and they ſhal be in mournynge and eueuerlaſtyng ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row which ſerueden to vyces / eyther vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable
<pb facs="tcp:20667:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->
deſyres. And as all theſe ſhal be worthy to be ordeyned / to the fyre of hell for theyr ſynnes / &amp; theyr great treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paces. So if we pleaſe God here / whyle we ben in body we ſhal take euerlaſtyng reward with ſayntes. Therfore deſpyſe we all thynges that be vayne &amp; fallyng / that we may get ſo great glory of Chriſt doyng mercy: therfore bowe we awaye fro vyces / and go we to vertues and let not ſuperflue wordes come out of our mouth. For we ſhal yeld rekenyng in the day of dome of all ydel wordes. Neyther make we our tong to haue cuſtom to cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyng / which tonge is formed to bles and herrie or prayſe God. For all thynges what euer is vnmeſured / maketh dyſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucyon of ſoule / &amp; neglygent agaynſt the lordes heſtes. Neyther he may lyghtely clepe or call his treſpaſces to mynd / and ſo forgettynge him ſelfe / ſtyreth not him ſelfe to penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / &amp; ſo by lytell &amp; lytell he paſſeth fro goodnes / &amp; he ſhall not haue true co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>punccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hert / where vnleful co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uetous
<pb facs="tcp:20667:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->
dwelleth. But ſothly where tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſhal be / there gooſtly fyre is kendled / which lyghteneth the preuyties of ſoule / and ſheweth to it heuenly thynges. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore vſe thou the felowſhyp of parfyt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and turne thou not away thyne eares fro theyr wordes / for the wordes of men dre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge god / ben wordes of lyfe and holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſoule to them that heere and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue them. For as the ſon ryſynge / dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth away the myſt / ſo the teachynge of holy men caſteth away darckneſſe of our hertes. Therfore I beſech you / eſchew proude men / enuyous men / backbyters / lyers / forſworen men / and men deſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng theyr helth / which ben deed in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues / and ioye in theyr owne luſtes and want goddes goodes. I ſay not only of them that ben in thyne houſe / but alſo where euer thou ſhalt heere ſuch / eſchew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; comune not with ſuch men / if thou mayſt not agayn clepe or call them from theyr errour: for why / oft by one ſcabbed ſheep / all the flocke is defyled. And a ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tel
<pb facs="tcp:20667:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->
part of gal turneth moch ſweetnes in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to bytternes. For though ſuch a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſeme to the clere in clothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; noble in bringing forth of ſwete wordes. Neuertheles if he doth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary warkes / ſuch faynyng of him noyeth more / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fygure eyther ſhap pleaſeth of wordes / &amp; euery warke that thou thynkeſt to do fyrſt / thynke thou on god / &amp; examyne diligently / if that thing which thou thynkeſt / be of god / and if it is ryghtfull before God / perfourme it / &amp; els cut it away fro thy ſoule / and beware of ech wyckednes and ſyn / in word / dede and thought / in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des / &amp; in fete / in ſight &amp; in heryng / &amp; kepe we our body &amp; ſoule for Ieſu Chriſt our lorde god / the ſon of god the father that came downe from he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to erth / he ſteyd vpon the croſſe / and dyed for vs ſynners to delyuer vs fro tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentynge of the deuyll / he ſuffred payne to delyuer vs fro euerlaſtynge payne / he ſuffred deth that we agayne ryſe in body &amp; ſoule / in the laſt day of the great dome And therfore it is ſayd of the fyrſt church
<pb facs="tcp:20667:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->
that one herte / one wyll / one ſoule / is to them in the lord. For the charite and loue Chriſt had coupled them into one / and ſo muſt all Chriſten men / if they wylen be ſaued. But fleſſhely men &amp; louers of this worlde ben departed agaynſt them ſelfe / and ben vnioyned / mouynge ſclaunders ech to other / ſtryues / wrathes / chidyngs diſſencyons / manſlaughters / forſweryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / theftes / rauenous / lecheries / dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſes / &amp; all thynges which the worlde loueth and the fleſſh. Of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtle ſayth: He that ſoweth in the fleſſh / ſhall repe corruption. In ſuche it is that the deuyl ſoweth his ſedes / forſoth our fleſſh wold euer be mighty in malice / but in ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtinence faſtynges / &amp; wakynges &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers / &amp; good workes / it fayneth it ſelfe to be ſyck / but the fleſſh coueyteth &amp; ſheweth euer euyll entyſynge / the fleſſhe ſtereth venemous doyng / the fleſh clepeth wrath the fleſſhe ſtereth manſleynge / the fleſſhe breketh matrymony / the fleſſh ſytteth in dronkenneſſe / the fleſſhe beareth all the
<pb facs="tcp:20667:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->
couetouſnes of this world / and the fleſſh deſyreth all the euyls. O thou wretched fleſſhe / not only thou ſleyeſt thy ſelfe but alſo thy ſoul: thy owne loſſe ſuffyſeth not to thy ſelf / but that alſo thy ſoule be dren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched or drouned into hel. Wo to the ſoule which hath taken the fleſſh / contrary to the which nether entreth / nether ſuffreth the to entre into the kyngdome of god.</p>
            <p>Wherfore as Chriſt ſayth: it behoueth to wake &amp; to pray. Lord / make y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> my ſoul to haue glorye in the / that vaynglory &amp; boſt come not out of me / but that bytternes of ſyn be aſwaged. Alſo lorde / gyue me gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce to hold rightwiſnes in all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / goſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly hardynes / temperans / &amp; make ſymple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes to be prudent in me / that I may lede a clenly bleſſed lyfe / &amp; prudently flye euel and that I maye vnderſtand the trecher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſe and the deſemblynge falſnes of the deuell / leſt he begyle me vnder lyknes of goodnes. Alſo make me to holde &amp; kepe theſe thinges: mylde / wel wyllyng / pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble / bonner / temperate / and to accorde
<pb facs="tcp:20667:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->
to all goodnes. Without faynyng / make me ſtedfaſt and ſtronge / in wakynge / in faſting / and in prayers, And alſo lorde / geue thou to me / in myldnes to be meſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in worde / that I kepe ſylens / that I ſpeke that thing that beſemeth me to ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / and that I hold ſtyll that thinge that beſemeth not to ſpeke. Geue me grace to kepe thy faith vndefyled without any er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in my workes / to be worthy of faith All theſe ſentences ſaith ſaint Auſten in his boke to the Earle,</p>
            <q>
               <p>HOC FAC ET VIVES.</p>
               <p>☞ Do this / and thou ſhalt lyue.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>☞ Imprynted at London in ſaynt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres paryſſh / in the old Bayly by Rychard Lant / for Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gough / dwellyng at Smartes kay beſyde byllynges gate</p>
         </div>
         <div type="privilege">
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
